Approximately 30 years ago,
قبل حوالي 30 عامًا،
when I was in oncology at the Children's Hospital
عندما كنت في قسم الأورام في مستشفى الأطفال
in Philadelphia,
في فيلاديلفيا،
a father and a son walked into my office
دخل أب مع ابنه إلى مكتبي
and they both had their right eye missing,
وكلاهما كان فاقد للعين اليمنى،
and as I took the history, it became apparent
وعندما أخذت تاريخهم المرضي، أصبح واضحًا
that the father and the son had a rare form
أن الأب وابنه يحملون نوعا نادرا
of inherited eye tumor, retinoblastoma,
من أورام العيون، اسمه ريتينوبلاستوما (ورم الشبكية)،
and the father knew that he had passed that fate
وقد علم الأب بأنه من نقل ذلك الورم
on to his son.
إلى ابنه.
That moment changed my life.
تلك اللحظة غيرت حياتي.
It propelled me to go on
ودفعتني للمضي قدمًا
and to co-lead a team that discovered
وأن أشارك في قيادة فريق اكتشف
the first cancer susceptibility gene,
أول مورثة لديها قابلية لتكوين سرطان،
and in the intervening decades since then,
وفي العقود المتوالية منذ ذلك الحين،
there has been literally a seismic shift
طرأ تحول مزلزل حرفيًا
in our understanding of what goes on,
لفهمنا لما يحدث،
what genetic variations are sitting behind
وماهي الاختلافات المورثية التي تتحكم في
various diseases.
أمرض مختلفة.
In fact, for thousands of human traits,
في الواقع، للألوف من الصفات البشرية،
a molecular basis that's known for that,
هناك قاعدة جزيئية معروفة لها،
and for thousands of people, every day,
وللألوف من البشر، كل يوم،
there's information that they gain
هناك معلومات يستقبلونها
about the risk of going on to get this disease
حول مخاطر الإصابة بهذا المرض
or that disease.
أو ذلك المرض.
At the same time, if you ask,
في نفس الوقت، لو سألت،
"Has that impacted the efficiency,
"هل أثر ذلك في كفاءة،
how we've been able to develop drugs?"
كيفية إنتاجنا للأدوية؟"
the answer is not really.
الجواب هو ليس كثيرًا.
If you look at the cost of developing drugs,
لو نظرت إلى تكلفة إنتاج الأدوية،
how that's done, it basically hasn't budged that.
كيف يأثر عليها ذلك، ستلاحظ أنها لم تتغير.
And so it's as if we have the power to diagnose
بالتالي أصبحنا نمتلك قوة التشخيص
yet not the power to fully treat.
ولم نمتلك قوة العلاج التام بعد.
And there are two commonly given reasons
هناك سببين عادةً ما تُقدّم
for why that happens.
لم حدث ذلك.
One of them is it's early days.
واحد منه أنه ما زال الوقت مبكر.
We're just learning the words, the fragments,
ما زلنا نتعلم الكلمات، الأجزاء،
the letters in the genetic code.
حروف الشفرة الوراثية.
We don't know how to read the sentences.
لا نعلم كيف نقرأ الجُمل.
We don't know how to follow the narrative.
لا نعلم كيف نتبع القصة.
The other reason given is that
السبب الثاني هو
most of those changes are a loss of function,
أغلب هذه التغيرات هي فقدان الوظيفة،
and it's actually really hard to develop drugs
وفي الحقيقة من الصعب جدًا إنتاج أدوية
that restore function.
تسترجع تلك الوظيفة.
But today, I want us to step back
لكن اليوم، أريدنا أن نرجع إلى الخلف
and ask a more fundamental question,
ونطرح سؤالا أكثر جوهرية
and ask, "What happens if we're thinking
نسأل، "ماذا سيحدث لو كنا نفكر
about this maybe in the wrong context?"
في ذلك ربما بطريقة خاطئة؟"
We do a lot of studying of those who are sick
نحن نقوم بدراسة الكثير من أولائك المرضى
and building up long lists
ونقوم بعمل قوائم طويلة
of altered components.
من المكونات المتغيرة.
But maybe, if what we're trying to do
لكن ربما، لو كنا نحاول أن
is to develop therapies for prevention,
نطوّر طريقة علاجية للوقاية،
maybe what we should be doing
ربما يفترض بنا أن نقوم
is studying those who don't get sick.
بدراسة أولئك الذين لا يمرضون.
Maybe we should be studying those
ربما يفترض بنا أن ندرس أولئك
that are well.
الأصحاء.
A vast majority of those people
الغالبية العظمى من أولئك الناس
are not necessarily carrying a particular
ليس بالضرورة أنهم يحملون
genetic load or risk factor.
مورثة معينة أو عامل خطر.
They're not going to help us.
هؤلاء لن يفيدونا.
There are going to be those individuals
هم أولئك الأشخاص
who are carrying a potential future risk,
الذين يحملون مخاطر مستقبلية محتملة،
they're going to go on to get some symptom.
سيمضون في إظهار بعض الأعراض.
That's not what we're looking for.
وذلك ليس هو ما نبحث عنه.
What we're asking and looking for is,
ما نسأل ونبحث عنه هو،
are there a very few set of individuals
تلك المجموعة الصغيرة من الأشخاص
who are actually walking around
الذين يتجولون ببساطة
with the risk that normally would cause a disease,
مع خطر عادةً قد يسبب المرض،
but something in them, something hidden in them
لكن شئ بداخلهم، شئ مخفي بداخلهم
is actually protective
هو في الواقع حماية لهم
and keeping them from exhibiting those symptoms?
ويقيهم من أن يظهروا هذه الأعراض؟
If you're going to do a study like that, you can imagine
لو أردت أن تقوم بدراسة كتلك، تصوّر
you'd like to look at lots and lots of people.
أنه يفترض بك فحص الكثير والكثير من الناس.
We'd have to go and have a pretty wide study,
يجب أن نقوم بعمل دراسة واسعة جدًا،
and we realized that actually
وقد أدركنا فعلًا
one way to think of this is,
طريقة واحدة لنفكر بها،
let us look at adults who are over 40 years of age,
دعنا نفحص البالغين فوق عمر الـ 40 سنة،
and let's make sure that we look at those
وأن نتأكد أننا نقوم بفحص
who were healthy as kids.
أولئك الذين كانوا أصحاء في طفولتهم.
They might have had individuals in their families
قد يكون هناك أشخاص في عوائلهم
who had had a childhood disease,
أصيبوا بأمراض في طفولتهم،
but not necessarily.
لكن ذلك ليس بالضررورة.
And let's go and then screen those
دعنا نقم بفحص هؤلاء
to find those who are carrying genes
بحثًا عمن يحملون مورثات
for childhood diseases.
لأمراض في الطفولة.
Now, some of you, I can see you
الآن، أرى أن البعض منكم
putting your hands up going, "Uh, a little odd.
قد وضع يديه كأنه يقول، "آه، ذلك غريب بعض الشيء.
What's your evidence
ما هو دليلك
that this could be feasible?"
على أن ذلك سيكون عملي؟"
I want to give you two examples.
أريد أن أعطيكم مثالين على ذلك.
The first comes from San Francisco.
الأول من سان فرانسيسكو.
It comes from the 1980s and the 1990s,
في عام 1980 و 1990،
and you may know the story where
من المحتمل أنكم تعرفون تلك القصة حيث
there were individuals who had very high levels
كان هناك أشخاص مصابين بمعدلات مرتفعة
of the virus HIV.
من فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية.
They went on to get AIDS.
قد أصيبوا بمرض الأيدز.
But there was a very small set of individuals
لكن كان هناك مجموعة صغيرة من الأشخاص
who also had very high levels of HIV.
كانوا أيضًا مصابين بمعدلات عالية من فيروس نقص المناعة.
They didn't get AIDS.
لم يصابوا بمرض الأيدز.
And astute clinicians tracked that down,
وقد فطن الأطباء لذلك ثم تعقبوه،
and what they found was they were carrying mutations.
وما وجدوه أن هؤلاء الأشخاص يحملون طفرة وراثية.
Notice, they were carrying mutations from birth
لاحظوا، كانوا يحملون طفرة منذ الولادة
that were protective, that were protecting them
كانت وقاية، كانت تحميهم
from going on to get AIDS.
من الإصابة بمرض الأيدز.
You may also know that actually a line of therapy
قد تعلمون أيضًا أن هناك خطة علاجية
has been coming along based on that fact.
طوّرت بناءً على تلك الحقيقة.
Second example, more recent, is elegant work
المثال الثاني، حدث مؤخرا، كان عملا مُشرّفا
done by Helen Hobbs,
قامت به هيلين هوبز،
who said, "I'm going to look at individuals
حيث قالت: "سأقوم بفحص الأشخاص
who have very high lipid levels,
الذين لديهم معدلات عالية من الدهون،
and I'm going to try to find those people
وسأحاول إيجاد أولئك الناس
with high lipid levels
الذين لديهم معدلات عالية من الدهون
who don't go on to get heart disease."
الذين لا يصابون بأمراض القلب."
And again, what she found was
ومرةً أخرى، ما وجدته
some of those individuals had mutations
كان أن بعض أولائك الأشخاص لديهم طفرات
that were protective from birth that kept them,
واقية وتحميهم منذ الولادة،
even though they had high lipid levels,
بالرغم من أن معدلات الدهون لديهم عالية،
and you can see this is an interesting way
تستطيعون أن تروا أن هذه طريقة شيقة
of thinking about how you could develop
من التفكير في كيفية تطوير
preventive therapies.
العلاجات الوقائية.
The project that we're working on
المشروع الذي نعمل عليه
is called "The Resilience Project:
يدعى "مشروع المرونة:
A Search for Unexpected Heroes,"
البحث عن أبطال غير متوقعين،"
because what we are interested in doing is saying,
لأن ما نهتم بعمله هو،
can we find those rare individuals
هل نستطيع إيجاد أولئك الأشخاص
who might have these hidden protective factors?
الذين قد يملكون تلك العناصر الخفية الواقية؟
And in some ways, think of it as a decoder ring,
وفي بعض الأحيان، فكروا فيها كخاتم لفك الشفرة،
a sort of resilience decoder ring
نوع من الخواتم لفك شفرة المرونة
that we're going to try to build.
هو ما نحاول أن نطوّره هنا.
We've realized that we should do this in a systematic way,
لقد أدركنا أننا يجب أن نعمل هذا بطريقة منظمة،
so we've said, let's take every single
لذلك قلنا، دعونا نأخذ كل
childhood inherited disease.
مرض وراثي في الطفولة.
Let's take them all, and let's pull them back a little bit
دعونا نأخذها كلها، ونرجعها إلى الوراء قليلًا
by those that are known to have severe symptoms,
عن طريق أولائك المعروفين بأن لديهم أعراض خطيرة،
where the parents, the child,
حيث أن الأبوين، والطفل،
those around them would know
أولئك الذين حولهم قد يعلمون
that they'd gotten sick,
أنهم مرضى،
and let's go ahead and then frame them again
ثم دعونا نأخذها إلى الأمام ونعد تشكيلها
by those parts of the genes where we know
بتلك الأجزاء من المورثات التي نعلم
that there is a particular alteration
أن هناك تغير معين
that is known to be highly penetrant
معروف أنه ذو نفاذية عالية بين الأجيال
to cause that disease.
في إحداث ذلك المرض.
Where are we going to look?
أين سنقوم بالفحص؟
Well, we could look locally. That makes sense.
حسنًا، سنفحص محليًا، ذلك منطقي.
But we began to think, maybe we should look
لكن بدأنا بالتفكير، أنه قد يفترض بنا الفحص
all over the world.
في كل أنحاء العالم.
Maybe we should look not just here
ربما لا يفترض بنا الفحص هنا فقط
but in remote places where their might be
لكن في أماكن بعيدة حيث قد يكون هناك
a distinct genetic context,
سياق وراثي منفصل،
there might be environmental factors
قد يكون هناك عوامل بيئية
that protect people.
تحمي الناس.
And let's look at a million individuals.
سنقوم بفحص ملايين الأشخاص.
Now the reason why we think it's a good time
السبب الذي يجعلنا نظن أن الوقت مناسب
to do that now
للقيام بذلك
is, in the last couple of years,
هو، أنه في السنوات الأخيرة،
there's been a remarkable plummeting in the cost
حدث هبوط ملحوظ في التكلفة
to do this type of analysis,
لعمل هذا النوع من تحليل البيانات،
this type of data generation,
هذا النوع من إصدار البيانات،
to where it actually costs less to do
حيث أن التكلفة لعمل
the data generation and analysis
تحليل وإصدار البيانات أقل
than it does to do the sample processing and the collection.
من تحليل العينة وجمعها.
The other reason is that in the last five years,
السبب الآخر هو أنه في الخمس سنوات الماضية،
there have been awesome tools,
أصبحت هنالك أدوات رائعة،
things about network biology, systems biology,
أشياء تخص الشبكات الحيوية، والأنظمة الحيوية،
that have come up that allow us to think
والتي ظهرت وسمحت لنا بالتفكير
that maybe we could decipher
في أننا قد نستطيع فك شفرة
those positive outliers.
تلك القيم الإيجابية المتطرفة.
And as we went around talking to researchers
وعندما بدأنا نتحدث مع الباحثين
and institutions
والمؤسسات
and telling them about our story,
ونخبرهم بقصتنا،
something happened.
حدث شيء ما.
They started saying, "This is interesting.
أصبحوا يقولون، "هذا رائع.
I would be glad to join your effort.
يسعدنا أن نوحد جهودنا.
I would be willing to participate."
يسعدنا المشاركة معكم."
And they didn't say, "Where's the MTA?"
لم يقولوا " ماهو الـ MTA؟"
They didn't say, "Where is my authorship?"
ولم يقولوا "أين حقوق ملكيتي؟"
They didn't say, "Is this data going to be mine? Am I going to own it?"
لم يقولوا، "هل ستصبح هذه البيانات ملكي؟ هل سأمتلكها؟"
They basically said, "Let's work on this
قالوا ببساطة، "هيا لنعمل عليها
in an open, crowd-sourced, team way
عمل جماعي مشترك ومفتوح المصدر
to do this decoding."
لنفك هذه الشفرة."
Six months ago, we locked down
قبل ستة أشهر، تمكنا من
the screening key for this decoder.
الحصول على مفتاح الفحص لفك هذه الشفرة.
at the Icahn Mount Sinai School of Medicine in New York,
في كلية طب إيكان ماونت سيناي في نيويورك،
and his team,
وفريقه،
locked in that decoder key ring,
تمكنوا من إيجاد مفتاح فك الشفرة،
and we began looking for samples,
وبدأنا نفحص العينات،
because what we realized is,
لأن ما أدركناه هو،
maybe we could just go and look
أننا قد نستطيع أن نقوم بفحص
at some existing samples to get some sense of feasibility.
عينات موجودة للحصول على نوع من دراسة الجدوى.
Maybe we could take two, three percent of the project on,
من الممكن أن نتقدم بالمشروع 2% أو 3%،
and see if it was there.
ونرى إن كانت موجودة هناك.
And so we started asking people
لذلك بدأنا بالطلب من الناس
such as Hakon at the Children's Hospital in Philadelphia.
مثل هاكون في مستشفى الأطفال في فيلاديلفيا.
We asked Leif up in Finland.
وليف في فينلندا.
We talked to Anne Wojcicki at 23andMe,
تكلمنا مع آن وجيكي و23andMe،
and Wang Jun at BGI,
وووانغ جن في BGI،
and again, something remarkable happened.
ومرة أخرى، حدث أمر رائع.
They said, "Huh,
لقد قالوا، "هه،
not only do we have samples,
ليس لدينا عينات فقط،
but often we've analyzed them,
بل غالبًا ما نكون قد حللناها،
and we would be glad to go into
ويسعدنا أن ننظر في
our anonymized samples
عيناتنا المجهولة المصدر
and see if we could find those
ونرى إن كان بالإمكان إيجاد أولئك
that you're looking for."
الذين تبحثون عنهم."
And instead of being 20,000 or 30,000,
وبدلًا من كون العينات 20,000 أو 30,000
last month we passed one half million samples
تخطينا الشهر الماضي نصف مليون عينة
that we've already analyzed.
والتي قمنا فعلًا بتحليلها.
So you must be going,
من المؤكد أنكم تتسائلون،
"Huh, did you find any unexpected heroes?"
"هه، وهل وجدتم أي من الأبطال الغير المتوقعين؟"
And the answer is, we didn't find one or two.
والجواب هو، أننا لم نجد واحد أو اثنين.
We found dozens of these strong candidate
بل وجدنا العشرات من المرشحين الأقوياء من
unexpected heroes.
الأبطال الغير متوقعين.
So we think that the time is now
نحن نعتقد الآن بأنه الوقت المناسب
to launch the beta phase of this project
لإطلاق النسخة بيتا من هذا المشروع
and actually start getting prospective individuals.
وبدأنا بالفعل في استقبال الأشخاص المحتملين.
Basically all we need is information.
مبدئيًا كل ما نحتاجه هو المعلومات.
We need a swab of DNA
نحتاج إلى مسحة من الـحمض النووي
and a willingness to say, "What's inside me?
ورغبة تقول، "ماذا بداخلي؟
I'm willing to be re-contacted."
أنا مستعد أن تعاودوا الإتصال بي."
Most of us spend our lives,
أغلبنا يقضي معظم حياته،
when it comes to health and disease,
عندما يتعلق الأمر بالصحة والمرض،
acting as if we're voyeurs.
بالتعامل معها كمسترق للنظر.
We delegate the responsibility
كلنا نفوض مسؤولية
for the understanding of our disease,
فهمنا لأمراضنا،
for the treatment of our disease,
وعلاجنا لأمراضنا،
to anointed experts.
للخبراء المختصين.
In order for us to get this project to work,
لجعل هذا المشروع يعمل من أجلنا
we need individuals to step up
نحتاج إلى أشخاص يتقدمون
in a different role and to be engaged,
في أدوار مختلفة ويلتزمون،
to realize this dream,
بتحقيق هذا الحلم،
this open crowd-sourced project,
هذا المشروع المفتوح المصدر،
to find those unexpected heroes,
لإيجاد أولئك الأبطال الغير متوقعين،
to evolve from the current concepts
للتقدم من المبادئ الحالية
of resources and constraints,
من الموارد والقيود،
to design those preventive therapies,
إلى تطوير العلاجات الوقائية،
and to extend it beyond childhood diseases,
وأخذها إلى أبعد من أمراض الطفولة،
to go all the way up to ways
لتشمل كل الطرق
that we could look at Alzheimer's or Parkinson's,
التي قد تمكننا من فحص مرض آلزهايمر أو باركينسون،
we're going to need us
سوف نحتاج إلى أنفسنا
to be looking inside ourselves and asking,
لننظر إلى ما بداخل أنفسنا ونسأل،
"What are our roles?
"ماهو دورنا؟
What are our genes?"
ماهي مورثاتنا؟"
and looking within ourselves for information
ننظر إلى ما بداخلنا من المعلومات
we used to say we should go to the outside,
والتي تعودنا أن نقول يجب أن نذهب للخارج،
to experts,
للخبراء،
and to be willing to share that with others.
وأن تكون لدينا الرغبة في مشاركتها مع الآخرين.
Thank you very much.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)